It's easy to customize your notes.

Make your notes stand out and get noticed.

• Format text using different fonts and font sizes
• Add emphasis with bold and italic text styles or color.
• Include graphics ￼ . 

Stickies has lots of other great features, including a spell checker, import and export features, and other ways to arrange and customize your notes. Plus, you'll find a "Make New Sticky Note" service in many applications.

Look in Help to find out more about using Stickies.

~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

Arduino can be ran off of 5V USB power or 9V battery power - only one is used
Voltage regulators - chips that convert 9V to two seperate voltages 5V and 3.3V

the second chip on the board is a USB to serial converter (USB to i2C). I2C is an old and simple way to communicate between computers. Any formal method that allows two chips to communicate is called a protocol. 

Oscillator:
it is a small physical crystal that is placed in such a way that when current is flowing through it, it vibrates very very fast (16 million times a second) and generates an electrical signal that the Arduino chip uses to coordinates its various parts. (16Mhz). 

Digital signal can only take one of the two values, 0 volts or 5 volts. 0 volts is called Ground and represented as either VCC or simply marked 5V. Just a note, there is also a 3.3V on Arduino that we will not be using. 

Arduino is an open source microcontrollers
There are 2 kinds of processors - micro controllers and microprocessors.

Microcontrollers:
they are really simple processors that can run ONLY one program at any one time. If you upload another program, the first one is erased. As soon as you attach power on the microcontroller, it starts the program that was saved on it and starts running it and keeps running it until the power is taken away

Computer Processor:
a single chip usually that can execute computer instruction

Microprocessors:
they are complex that can run multiple programs at the same time. In general, they have what is called an Operating System that runs on top of them . You run your programs on top of the Operating System 

Microcontrollers:
usually quite rugged and easy to use for electronic prototyping. Microprocessors although powerful usually are more fragile by nature.


Buzzer module:

piezo-electric crystal:  that vibrates by switching it on and of very quickly - we can produce many different frequencies of sound

GPIO: general purpose input output this refers to a digital or analog pin on Arduino that can be controlled by softwareUsually, this is where we connect other electronic devices

negative(-) goes GND 
s goes to pin 5(digital)
middle min that is not marked goes to 5V

int c = 3830
int d = 3400
int e = 3038
int f = 2864
int g = 2550
int a = 2272
int b = 2028 
int c = 1912
int r = 0 // rest 

NOTES:

serial communication is a form of a computer that works over slow connections. it was invented in the 1970s. it talks about bandwidth, or speed of transfer in bits per second. One baud = i bit per second.


WIRING THE LED PANEL
- vcc to 5V
- gnd to ground
- int DIN Pin = 12;
- int CLK Pin = 11;
- int CS Pin = 10; 



POWERED USB HUB

-connect the USB hub to power - it had an adapter which should be plugged in before you plug in USB hub to your computer
-motors draw a lot of current! Your computer USB has limit of 500mA usually. That can damage your computer. The USB provides a buffer
-USB hub can provide up to 2A current

HOW TO WIRE THE ULTRASONIC SENSOR

-vcc to 5v
-gnd to ground
-trig to pin 6
-echo to pin 7
										      
ultrasonic sensor - based on sound reflection.    

-a wave frequency is 40khz
-sensor sends 8 pulses in quick succession
-then it waits for the echo to come back and measures the echo duration. Based on the duration of echo, you can figure out the distance

~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

FTC

The electronic configuration:
- one phone stays in your hand called the DRIVER STATION PHONE. it contains the driver station app
- the other phone is on the robot called the Robot Controller Phone and contains the Robot Container App - you can modify the code on the app
- the phones are connected via WIFI direct - a peer to peer direct communication wireless protocol
-once configured, your phones should not connect to WIFI/internet


Robot Controller App

teleop mode - controller using remote
autonomous - robot does operations by itself

FTCRobotController (unzip) > java > ... >harward pushbot & pushbot telcop
paste the two files at - teamcode > java > org.firstinspires

configuration of the robot is called the - hardware map
it contains the devices i.e motors and sensors and the name you give them on the robot controller phone when you configure it

class is basically like a container that can hold things like variables and functions
class is like the house - public is like the public area in the house that is public to everyone 
----------
hardware pushbot class takes all the stuff and combines it/ configures it

teleop are stand alone programs that denote a robot mission

inside of teleop
___________________________             ________________________   
|      hardware push bot      |            | hardware configuration|
|.       class gets.                 |            | that we created on the |
|         this configuration     | -->    |    phone before             |
|                                         |            |                                     |
|__________________________|            |_______________________|

Syntax

init - is basically initialize the robot to say what it is doing
leftmotor/rightmotor - variable created that declares the actual motor - whether it is the right or left 
Autonomous - the robot will be running in autonomous mode 
telemetry - the information is being passed from one phone to the other

encoder  = tacometer (counts degrees)
annotations = the class will have special properties

_____________                        _____________                ____
|   Driver.     |                      |   Robot        |         ___|.     |____
|. Station      |                      | controller.   |        |. Hardware. |
|.  phone.     |    )) WIFI. --- |   phone       |. -->|___        ____|
|________ ___|                       | ____________|             |____|

1. You go to the controller phone and create the configuration.
2. Yo go to your FTC app code and ask for the configuration.
3. Once you have the configuration, you extracted the classes from it.
4. Finally, you can control it using Op modes- which are the actual programs that move the robot

While loop
while(true)//or false -- boolean condition
{
	counter++.  ///it basically increases it by one
	System.out.println(counter);
}

--------------------------------

The controller phone first connects to your computer, then you modify the Teleop code and upload it to the controller app on the phone.

After that you disconnect the controller phone and connect to the controller phone. After that, make sure that the controller and driver station phons are connected in the Ui of the apps. 

then , using the Driver Station menus (in the top right corner) use "restart Robot" that should clear out all the errors

if you are using a remote control kind of teleop, then press 'start' button on the joystick and tap the 'a' button. This should show up the joystick icon on the driver station. 

next you can select your teleop from the drop down on the driver station and run it.

MOTOR TYPES

- DC motors 
	- with and without encoders
- Servo motors
	- DC motors wth potentiometers (variable registor) 
	- will turn only 180 degrees
	- can be commanded to go to any degree from 0 to 180. 
	- extremely accurate
	- used in making grippers, pickers, throwers, plows, etc
- Continuous Rotation Servos 
	- same as the 180 degrees servos except  that they continue to turn 
	- it measures the degrees - has encoder
	-  much weaker than regular DC motors and not used regularly 


		___________________
		|				|
		|				|
		|				|
_________|				|
|	 ____			 ____		|
|____(      )_________(      )____|
         --                   --

input/output for java

Scanner input = new Scanner(System.in);
Scanner sc = new Scanner(System.in);
int i = sc.nextInt();

System.out.println(i);

Thread.sleep(100);
System.out,println("Enter a string....");

String s = sc.next();
System.out.println(s);
 



Game Programming
-A game is a program that really never finishes
-Game has 3 parts : read input from the user, update positions of objects on screen, draw all the objects on screen
-The above is done in an infinite loop

 



----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------


Innovation

Servers:
-they are basically computers in the cloud. They are essentially large machines that support 4 major operations over something known as 

Protocol:
it is a way that 2 entities communicate

Statelessness:
it means when a server will do what you ask it to do, but will not remember what it did after it is done doing what it was doing

Talking with a server had multiple components:
1. the URL (uniform resource locator) - this is the location you are trying to hit and get to
2. if you are sending data to the server, you need to tell the sever 'what you are trying to send' ex. text, image, or video
3. the actual  content whatever you are trying to send to the server


---

Webserver:
- it is program that takes a few files in HTML format and sends it back to the computers that connect to it
- the way a web server and a browser communicate is called HTTP 
- web server written in python has python functions that take input and produce outputs
- we use a webserver when we need to create a way for our website or content to be available to multiple people
- developers use python code that runs on those web addresses
- so web servers point to python code

Routing Table - the table that maps the web address to the python function

HTML:
as part of each python function responsible for a route, we need to produce valid HTML and send it back a the return output

